<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<?xml-model href="Schemas/flowersEditingConsistencyRules.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<topic id="id_kvj_bwn_fw">
  <title>Growing Flowers</title>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>With just a little bit of care and preparation, any flower garden can be a vibrantly
        colored environment. Flowers can be selected for specific blooming seasons, colors and
        shapes. Both annual and perennial flower gardens can be planted depending on climate and
        specific needs.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Flowers by Season</title>
      <p>The various climatic changes that occur in cyclic pattern are termed as 'Seasons'. There
        are four general seasons occurring on Earth - Spring, Summer, Autumn and Winter.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>Spring Time, the time of growth and renewal of new plant and animal life. Spring comes
          at different times in the North and South Hemispheres. Spring time in the Northern
          hemisphere is between March - May, and between September - November in the Southern
          hemisphere. </li>
      </ul>
      <ul>
        <li>Summer is the time of hot and warm weather. Floral growth is the best in the summer
          season. The Northern hemisphere experiences summer during June, July, August, while in
          Southern hemisphere during December - February.</li>
        <li>Autumn is the season of the primary harvest. Autumn falls during September - November in
          the Northern hemisphere, and during March - June in the Southern hemisphere. Crops are
          harvested during Autumn. Leaves change color are at their beautiful best.</li>
        <li>Winter is the season of cold weather. The season occurs during December - February in
          Northern hemisphere. In the Southern hemisphere winter occurs during June - August. </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
