<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/06/schema/xmlspec.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<spec>
    <header>
        <title>Schematron Quick Fixes Specification</title>
        <w3c-designation>W3C Designation</w3c-designation>
        <w3c-doctype>Quick-fix support for XML Community Group &#x2013; Draft</w3c-doctype>
        <pubdate>
            <month>July</month>
            <year>2016</year>
        </pubdate>
        <publoc>
            <loc href="http://schematron-quickfix.github.io/sqf/spec/SQFSpec.html">schematron-quickfix.github.io/sqf/spec/SQFSpec.html</loc>
        </publoc>
        <latestloc>
            <loc href="http://schematron-quickfix.github.io/sqf/spec/SQFSpec.html">schematron-quickfix.github.io/sqf/spec/SQFSpec.html</loc>
        </latestloc>
        <authlist>
            <author>
                <name>Nico Kutscherauer</name>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Octavian Nadolu</name>
            </author>
        </authlist>
        <copyright>
            <p>Copyright © 2016, published by the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/quickfix/"
                    >Quick-fix support for XML Community Group</loc> under the <xspecref
                    href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla/">W3C Community
                    Contributor License Agreement (CLA)</xspecref>. A human-readable <xspecref
                    href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla-deed/">summary</xspecref>
                is available. </p>
        </copyright>
        <status>
            <p><emph>This specification was published by the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/quickfix/">Quick-fix support for XML Community Group</loc>. It is not a W3C Standard nor is it on the W3C Standards Track. Please note that under the <xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla/">W3C Community Contributor License Agreement (CLA)</xspecref> there is a limited opt-out and other conditions apply. Learn more about <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/">W3C Community and Business Groups</loc>.</emph></p>
            <p>Second Draft</p>
        </status>
        <abstract>
            <p>Schematron QuickFix is an extension of Schematron (standard ISO/IEC 19757-3:2006). Schematron QuickFix enables developers to define QuickFixes for Schematron errors. QuickFix implementations should present these QuickFixes for the reported Schematron errors to the user. The user can then decide which QuickFix fixes the error in an acceptable way.</p>
        </abstract>
        <langusage>
            <language>English</language>
        </langusage>
        <revisiondesc>
            <p>Revision description</p>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <body>
        <div1 id="namespaces_and_prefixes">
            <head>Namespaces and prefixes</head>
            <p>This document describes nodes that belong to different namespaces. All nodes that do not belong to the NULL namespace are give a prefix in order to distinguish them. The following table assigns a namespace URI to each prefix used in this document:</p>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Prefix</th>
                        <th>Namespace URI</th>
                        <th>Corresponding standard</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td>sch</td>
                        <td>http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron</td>
                        <td>ISO Schematron</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>sqf</td>
                        <td>http://www.schematron-quickfix.com/validator/process</td>
                        <td>Schematron QuickFix</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>xsl</td>
                        <td>http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform</td>
                        <td>XSLT 2.0</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
        </div1>
        <div1 id="terminology">
            <head>Terminology</head>
            <glist>
                <gitem>
                    <label id="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</label>
                    <def>
                        <p>Condition which is declared by the Schematron elements <el>sch:report</el> or <el>sch:assert</el>.</p>
                        <p>A failed Schematron assertion produces a <termref def="sch-error">Schematron error</termref>. One Schematron assertion can produce multiple <termref def="sch-error">Schematron errors</termref>. </p>
                    </def>
                </gitem>
                <gitem>
                    <label id="sch-rule">Schematron rule</label>
                    <def>
                        <p>According to the Schematron element <el>sch:rule</el>. It contains one or more <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertions</termref>.</p>
                        <glist>
                            <gitem id="sch-rule-context">
                                <label>Context</label>
                                <def>
                                    <p>The context of a <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rule</termref> is defined by the attribute <att>context</att>. If a rule matches to more than one node, it has more than one context. </p>
                                </def>
                            </gitem>
                        </glist>
                    </def>
                </gitem>
                <gitem>
                    <label id="sch-error">Schematron error</label>
                    <def>
                        <p>A Schematron error occurs if a <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref> failed for one context of its <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rule</termref>.</p>
                        <glist>
                            <gitem>
                                <label id="sch-error-context">Context</label>
                                <def>
                                    <p>The context of the <termref def="sch-error">Schematron error</termref> is the node, which was matched by the Schematron rule, when the <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref> failed.</p>
                                    <p>The attribute <att>subject</att> has no affect to the context of the Schematron error. Unlike to the <termref def="sch-rule-context">context of the Schematron rule</termref>, the Schematron error has only one context node.</p>
                                </def>
                            </gitem>
                        </glist>
                    </def>
                </gitem>

            </glist>
        </div1>
        <div1 id="introduction">
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>This section describes the classification of the based concepts of Schematron QuickFix.</p>
            <div2 id="fix">
                <head>Fix</head>
                <p>A fix is a change of a document, applied to an occurred error. All changes must have the object to solve this error. Requirement is to detect the error first.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="quick-fix-concept">
                <head>Quick fix</head>
                <p>A Quick fix is a fully automatic implemented fix. In connection with an error (produced by a validation of a document) one ore more Quick fixes are offered to execute. A user can choose the Quick fix, which is executed by a fully automated process. </p>
                <p>A Quick fix requires: </p>
                <olist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Instructions, written in a document processing language, to implement the fix. The instructions have to designed in a way, that it is able to process them applied to a context. The context is defined by the occurred error.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>A human-readable description of the Quick fix. The description should be displayed to the user, when he chooses the Quick fix.</p>
                    </item>
                </olist>
                <p>It is able to define Quick fixes inside of a validation parser or using a therefore designed script language. First, there is a limited quantity of Quick fixes, in the second case the quantity is unlimited.</p>
                <p>It depends on the quantity of unique kinds of errors from the validation language, which way makes more sense. Is the quantity of kinds of errors limited, an implementation of Quick fixes inside of the parser is possible.</p>
                <p>Basic requirements for an implementation of a Quick fix workflow:</p>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Definition of Quick fixes (embedding into a parser or into a validation language).</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>A workflow to execute the Quick fixes.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Graphical user interface to choose the Quick fixes.</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist>
            </div2>
        </div1>
        <div1 id="workflow">
            <head>Workflow</head>
            <p>Schematron QuickFix (SQF) is an extension of the validation language Schematron to embed Quick fixes. To provide an overview of the Schematron QuickFix concept, this section describes the integration of SQF into the Schematron workflow.</p>
            <note>
                <p>Please note the different spelling of <emph>QuickFix</emph> and <emph>Quick fix</emph>. The spelling QuickFix means a Quick fix of the extension language Schematron QuickFix. The spelling Quick fix means a nonspecific Quick fix, which was described in the section <titleref href="#quick-fix-concept">Quick fix</titleref>.</p>
            </note>
            <p>The following figure shows the SQF workflow in eight steps:</p>
            <graphic source="img/workflow.png" alt="Workflow diagram with eight numbered steps that correspond to the eight sections in this chapter." />
            <p>The following sections describes each step of the workflow diagram and its difference to the conventional Schematron workflow.</p>
            <div2 id="schematron_validation">
                <head>Schematron validation</head>
                <p>The workflow starts with a classic Schematron validation process. There are no changes needed for Schematron QuickFix, but a preferred way to implement the QuickFixes is, to compile them during the basic Schematron validation. </p>
                <p>For this specification, the following terms will be used to describe the documents, which are subject of this step:</p>
                <glist>
                    <gitem>
                        <label id="sch-source-document">Source document</label>
                        <def>
                            <p>The document, which is validated. If there are multiple documents, which are connected by using XInclude, these documents will be considered as one document. If there are multiple documents, which will be validated to one Schematron schema (for instance during a validation of documents of a folder), this validations will be considered as multiple separated validations.</p>
                        </def>
                    </gitem>
                    <gitem>
                        <label>Schematron schema</label>
                        <def>
                            <p>The <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref> will be validated against the Schematron schema. If there are multiple schematron documents, which are connected by include techniques of Schematron, these documents will be considered as one document. If there are multiple schematron schemas are associated with the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref> (for instance by more than one <code>xml-model</code> processing instructions), the validations by each schema will be considered as multiple separated validations.</p>
                        </def>
                    </gitem>
                </glist>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="validation_result_check">
                <head>Validation result check</head>
                <p>The second step is the validation result check. If the validation result is true, the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref> is valid and the next step is <titleref href="#step8">step 8</titleref>. If the validation result is false, there are errors detected.</p>
                <p>In this step, there is no changes for Schematron QuickFix necessary.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="error_report">
                <head>Error report</head>
                <p>The error report should be generated by the Schematron validation. The implementation is free to use a proprietary or a standardised structur for this report (SVRL for example). </p>
                <p>In this step, changes for Schematron QuickFix are not needed, but it is a possible way, to implement Schematron QuickFix, by extending the SVRL or any other maybe existing report structure, so the report is able to contain the compiled QuickFixes.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="show_the_errors_in_the_source_document">
                <head>Show the errors in the source document</head>
                <p>The last step of the classic Schematron validation workflow is, to display the detected errors, by using the error message in connection with the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref>.</p>
                <p>A required change for Schematron QuickFix is, to display the available QuickFixes for those errors, in relation to the Schematron error.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="decision_of_the_user">
                <head>Decision of the user</head>
                <p>The Schematron QuickFix user should have an interactive option to select one or more QuickFixes to execute it. This is a new step for Schematron QuickFix only.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="workflow_fix_process">
                <head>Executing a Quick fix</head>
                <p>Depending on the decision of the user, the selected QuickFix(es) will be executed. Normally the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref> will be the source of this fix process and will be replaced by the result of this process. But the implementation could support QuickFixes for external documents (<titleref href="#example_external_doc">See example in Appendix</titleref>). In this cases each external document will be the source of a separate fix process and replaced by the result.</p>
                <p>This is also a new step for Schematron QuickFix only.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="validation_after_the_fix">
                <head>Validation after the fix</head>
                <p>After each execution of a QuickFix, a new validation of the changed document is necessary to update the error report or to get a positive validation result. This is equal to a new Schematron validation in a classic Schematron workflow, which is necessary if there are any changes on the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref>.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="step8">
                <head>Fixed document</head>
                <p>The fixed document, which does not contains any errors any more is the target of each Schematron validation. There is no changes for Schematron QuickFix.</p>
            </div2>
        </div1>
        <div1 id="language">
            <head>Language</head>
            <p>This section describes the meanings of the Schematron QuickFix syntax.</p>
            <div2 id="embedding_into_schematron">
                <head>Embedding into Schematron</head>
                <p>To embed Schematron QuickFix into Schematron, all extending elements should have the namespace <code>http://www.schematron-quickfix.com/validator/process</code> (preferred prefix <code>sqf</code>).</p>
                <p>The following table shows the permitted parent-child relations between the namespaces of SQF and Schematron.</p>
                <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="10">
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Parent element</th>
                            <th>Permitted children</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sch:schema</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sqf:fixes</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sch:rule</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sqf:fix</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sqf:group</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:title</el>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:name</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:value-of</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:p</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:name</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:value-of</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:emph</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:dir</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:span</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:fix</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:let</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
                <p>The following table shows which attributes from the SQF namespace should be permitted of which Schematron elements:</p>
                <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="10">
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Schematron element</th>
                            <th>Permitted SQF attribute</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:assert</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><att>sqf:fix</att></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><att>sqf:default-fix</att></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:report</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><att>sqf:fix</att></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><att>sqf:default-fix</att></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="quick-fix">
                <head>QuickFix</head>
                <p>A QuickFix requires the following properties:</p>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Description with at least a title</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>ID</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>One or more change commands (see <titleref href="#change-commands">Change commands</titleref>)</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist>
                <p>A QuickFix is able to have the following additional properties:</p>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Additional documentation as a part of the description</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Condition to provide the QuickFix</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Loop to make the QuickFix generic (see <titleref href="#generic-fixes">Generic QuickFix</titleref>)</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>User Entry to parametrise the QuickFix (see <titleref href="#user-entry">User Entries</titleref>)</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist>
                <note>
                    <p>Please note that the properties does not need to be declared directly in the coresponding <el>sqf:fix</el> element, but could also be adopted of other QuickFixes by calling them (<el>sqf:call-fix</el> element).</p>
                </note>
                <div3 id="definition_of_a_quickfix">
                    <head>Definition of a QuickFix</head>
                    <p>The QuickFix is defined by the <el>sqf:fix</el> element. The requirements will be satisfied with the following base structure:</p>
                    <p><example>
                            <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sqf:fix id="fix1">
    &lt;sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:title>Fix 1&lt;/sqf:title>
    &lt;/sqf:description>
    [Elements from the content model  (sqf:delete | sqf:add | sqf:replace | sqf:stringReplace | sqf:call-fix)+]
&lt;/sqf:fix></eg>
                        </example></p>
                    <p>The defined QuickFix above has the following properties:</p>
                    <p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Description / title: Fix 1</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>ID: fix1</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>One or more change commands: not specified yet.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                    </p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="quickfixes_id">
                    <head>QuickFixes ID</head>
                    <p>The ID of the QuickFix and the <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref> is the Identifier to reference QuickFixes and <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref>.</p>
                    <p>Requirements to set the ID:<ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>The ID has to correspond with the XSD type xs:NCName.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Inside of a <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rule</termref> the ID must be unique.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">Global</titleref> QuickFixes or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref> should not have the same IDs.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist></p>
                    <p>In the following cases it is permitted that two QuickFixes, <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref> or a QuickFix and a <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> have the same IDs:<ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p><?oxy_comment_start author="octavian_nadolu" timestamp="20151015T122111+0300" comment="Maybe we need to specify which fix is used in this case."?>One is <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">global</titleref> the other is <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">local</titleref>.<?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_start author="Nico Kutscherauer" timestamp="20151116T092206-0500" comment="I added a description in the section &quot;Scope&quot;"?></p>
                                <?oxy_comment_end?>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Both are <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">local</titleref>, but declared in different <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rules</termref>.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist></p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="quick-fix.global-local">
                    <head>Global and local QuickFixes</head>
                    <p>A QuickFix or a <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> can be defined <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">global</titleref> or <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">local</titleref>. <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">Local</titleref> QuickFixes or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref> are declared inside of the <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rule</termref> and only the <termref def="sch-assertion">assertions</termref> of this rule are able to refer to the QuickFixes or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref>. <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">Global</titleref> QuickFixes or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref> are declared inside of the <el>sqf:fixes</el> element and available for all <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertions</termref> (see below <titleref href="#quick-fix.reference.scope">Scope</titleref>).</p>
                    <example>
                        <p>Example for a <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">global</titleref> QuickFix:</p>
                        <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sch:schema> 
     [...] 
     &lt;sqf:fixes>
          &lt;sqf:fix id="fix2"> [...] &lt;/sqf:fix>
     &lt;/sqf:fixes>
&lt;/sch:schema></eg>
                    </example>
                    <example>
                        <p>Example for a <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">local</titleref> QuickFix:</p>
                        <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sch:rule context="[...]">
     [...] 
     &lt;sqf:fix id="fix1"> [...] &lt;/sqf:fix>
&lt;/sch:rule></eg>
                    </example>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="quick-fix.reference">
                    <head>Reference to a QuickFix</head>
                    <p><termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertions</termref> are able to refer to one or more QuickFixes or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref> or a mix of QuickFixes and <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref>. Therefore the <att>sqf:fix</att> attribute contains a whitespace separated list of IDs. Each ID has to refer to an ID of a QuickFix or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref>. The amount of references are unbounded, but implementations are able to set a limit.</p>
                    <example>
                        <p>The <el>sch:assert</el> element refers to the QuickFixes with the ID <attval>fix1</attval> and <attval>fix2</attval>:</p>
                        <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sch:assert test="[...]" sqf:fix="fix1 fix2">[...]&lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;sqf:fix id="fix1"> 
    [...] 
&lt;/sqf:fix> 
&lt;sqf:fix id="fix2">
    [...] 
&lt;/sqf:fix></eg>
                    </example>
                    <div4 id="quick-fix.reference.scope">
                        <head>Scope</head>
                        <p><termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertions</termref> are only able to refer to QuickFixes or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref> wich are in scope of its <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rules</termref>. </p>
                        <p>
                            <ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>A <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">local</titleref> QuickFix or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> is in scope, if its <el>sqf:fix</el> or <el>sqf:group</el> element is a descendent element of the same <el>sch:rule</el> element as the refering <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref>.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>A <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">global</titleref> QuickFix or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> is in scope of any <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rules</termref> of the Schematron Schema, except there is a <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">local</titleref> QuickFix or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> with the same ID in the scope of the <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rules</termref>.</p>
                                </item>
                            </ulist>
                        </p>
                        <p role="error-def" id="references_1">It is an error, if a <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertions</termref> refers to a QuickFix or <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref>, which is not in the scope of its <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rules</termref>.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="providing_conditions">
                        <head>Providing conditions</head>
                        <p>Is a <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref> producing a <termref def="sch-error">Schematron error</termref> that refers to a QuickFix, a Schematron QuickFix implementation may provide the QuickFix as a choice for the user to execute the QuickFix in connection to the occurred error.</p>
                        <p><emph>Exceptions:</emph>
                        </p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>A QuickFix, which condition was not satisfied in the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref>, should not be provided.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>A <titleref href="#generic-fixes">generic QuickFix</titleref> may not able to be provided in some cases (see <titleref href="#generic-fixes">Generic QuickFix section</titleref>)</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>It is up to the implementation to provide QuickFixes which has no change commands or uses elements which are not supported by the implementation.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="default_quickfix">
                        <head>Default QuickFix</head>
                        <p>The <att>sqf:default-fix</att> attribute is provided to set a default QuickFix for a <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref>. The attribute value should be the id of a QuickFix.</p>
                        <p role="error-def" id="default-fix_1">It is an error, if the default QuickFix is not referred by the <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref> (using the <att>sqf:fix</att> attribute).</p>
                        <p>An implementation is free, how to handle the default QuickFix.</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="execution_of_a_quickfix">
                    <head>Execution of a QuickFix</head>
                    <p>During the execution process of a QuickFix each <titleref href="#change-commands">change command</titleref> will be executed in the <termref def="sch-error-context">context node of the error</termref>, if their condition was satisfied in this context.</p>
                    <div4 id="execution_of_more_than_one_quickfix">
                        <head>Execution of more than one QuickFix</head>
                        <p>It is free to the implementation to allow executions of more than one QuickFix at once. But an execution of more than one QuickFix of the same <termref def="sch-error">Schematron error</termref> at once are not permitted.</p>
                        <p>It is up to the implementation to warn the user against <titleref href="#conflicts">possible conflicts</titleref> or to hide QuickFixes to avoid such conflicts.</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="quick-fix.group">
                    <head>QuickFix group</head>
                    <p>A <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> is a set of one or more QuickFixes. The QuickFix will be implemented with the <el>sqf:group</el> element. Additional it needs an ID, specified by a mandatory <att>id</att> attribute.</p>
                    <p>A <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref> is able to refer to a <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> on the same way it refers to a QuickFix. A reference to a <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> is equal to references to all QuickFixes which the <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> contains. </p>
                    <p><example>
                            <p>The <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref> has the ID groupid and contains the QuickFixes with the IDs fix1 and fix2.</p>
                            <p>The first <el>sch:assert</el> element refers to the QuickFixes fix1 and fix2 per QuickFix ID. The second one refers to the same QuickFixes per ID of the <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref>.</p>
                            <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sch:assert test="[...]" sqf:fix="fix1 fix2">[...]&lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;sch:assert test="[...]" sqf:fix="groupid">[...]&lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;sqf:group id="groupid">
     &lt;sqf:fix id="fix1"> [...] &lt;/sqf:fix>
     &lt;sqf:fix id="fix2"> [...] &lt;/sqf:fix>
&lt;/sqf:group></eg>
                        </example></p>
                    <p>For more information see the <titleref href="#sqf_group">sqf:group</titleref> definition in the SQF reference.</p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="generic-fixes">
                    <head>Generic QuickFix</head>
                    <p>A generic QuickFix is different from a regular QuickFix in that it is defined for an unbounded count of provided QuickFixes. The count of provided QuickFixes may depend on the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref>.</p>
                    <p>To create a generic QuickFix, the <el>sqf:fix</el> element gets a <att>use-for-each</att> attribute. The <att>use-for-each</att> attribute expects an XPath expression. For each returned value or item of the XPath expression a QuickFix should be provided to the user. The XPath expression will be evaluated in the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref>. </p>
                    <p>The XPath expression of the<?oxy_comment_start author="octavian_nadolu" timestamp="20151015T140641+0300" comment="We should update also the XML Schema."?>
                        <att>use-for-each</att><?oxy_comment_end?><?oxy_comment_start author="Nico Kutscherauer" timestamp="20151024T101342+0200" comment="Added already in revision 44"?>
                        <?oxy_comment_end?>attribute does not change the context of the generic QuickFix. To access to the currently returned item/value, a build-in XPath variable <code>$sqf:current</code> (in the SQF namespace) should be provided. The <code>$sqf:current</code> variable should be available in each XPath expression inside of the <el>sqf:fix</el> element, which has an <att>use-for-each</att> attribute.</p>
                    <p>It should be an error, if the <code>$sqf:current</code> variable was used in a <el>sqf:fix</el> element, which does not have an <att>use-for-each</att> attribute.</p>
                    <p><example>
                            <p>Example:</p>
                            <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sqf:fix id="generic-fix" use-for-each="//*[@id]">
      &lt;sqf:description>
          &lt;sqf:title>Delete element &lt;value-of select="$sqf:current/@id"/>&lt;/sqf:title>
     &lt;/sqf:description>
     &lt;sqf:delete match="$sqf:current"/>
&lt;/sqf:fix></eg>
                            <p>For each element in the document which has an <att>id</att> attribute the implementation should provide one QuickFix. The title of those QuickFixes should be the fix string "Delete element " concatenated with the value of the corresponding <att>id</att> attribute. The change command will be, to delete the corresponding element.</p>
                        </example></p>
                    <div4 id="maximum_number_of_provided_quickfixes">
                        <head>Maximum number of provided QuickFixes</head>
                        <p>Please note, that it will be easy to create a high number of QuickFixes for each <termref def="sch-error">Schematron error</termref> using this structure. To handle this, an implementation is free to set a limit of allowed providing QuickFixes for generic QuickFixes. If a generic QuickFix violates this limit, the implementation is free to do not provide any QuickFixes or to occur an error. </p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="role">
                    <head>Role</head>
                    <p>The role is a meta data of the QuickFix. The role of a QuickFix describes the type of change which it makes. There are five types of changes:<ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p><attval>add</attval></p>
                                <p>The QuickFix adds nodes to the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref>.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><attval>delete</attval></p>
                                <p>The QuickFix deletes nodes in the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref>.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><attval>replace</attval></p>
                                <p>The QuickFix replace nodes from the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref> by new nodes.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><attval>stringReplace</attval></p>
                                <p>The QuickFix replace parts of text nodes in the source document by new nodes.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><attval>mix</attval></p>
                                <p>This is a fallback role type, if the QuickFix do more things or no type of change matches to the QuickFix.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist></p>
                    <p>An implementation is free to support other additional roles. There are two ways to define the role of a QuickFix:</p>
                    <p>
                        <olist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Automatically &#x2013; the implementation detects the role by the contained Activity Elements. The implementation is free to define own criteria to detect the role type.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Manually &#x2013; the developer overwrite the role manually using the <att>role</att> attribute:</p>
                                <example>
                                    <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sqf:fix id="replaceAtttribute" role="replace">
     [...]
     &lt;sqf:add match="*[@id]" target="id" node-type="attribute" select="generate-id()"/>
&lt;/sqf:fix></eg>
                                    <p>The implementation may detect the role type <attval>add</attval>, because the <el>sqf:add</el> element was used only. But the developer knows, that this QuickFix will replace the value of the <att>id</att> attribute anytime, so he set the role manually.</p>
                                </example>
                            </item>
                        </olist>
                    </p>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="change-commands">
                <head>Change commands</head>
                <p>A QuickFix needs at least one change command. A change command is implemented by an activity element (see element group <titleref href="#sqf_activityElements"><phrase><code>sqf:activityElements</code></phrase></titleref>). A change command is processed relative to an <titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">anchor node</titleref>.</p>
                <div3 id="change-command-anchor-node">
                    <head>Anchor node</head>
                    <p>The anchor node is the context of a change command. By default the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref> is the anchor node.</p>
                    <p>To specify anchor nodes, the <att>match</att> attribute is provided to each activity element. If an activity element points to more than one anchor node, for each anchor node the change command will be executed. If an activity element points to no anchor node, no change command will be executed.</p>
                    <p>The <att>match</att> attribute expects an XPath expression. The context of relative expressions is the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref>. It is recommended to allow expressions which can use the full functionality of XPath 2.0 (or newer) and additionally the XSLT 2.0 functions.</p>
                    <div4 id="anchor_node_restrictions">
                        <head>Requirements of the Anchor node / match attribute</head>
                        <p>The only restriction to the XPath expression of the match attribute, is that the type of the return value needs to be <code>node()*</code>. Any return values which does not match to this type should occurs an error.</p>
                        <p>An implementation is free to set further restrictions to the XPath expressions. If a Change command violates this restrictions, the implementation is free to occurs an error, to hide the corresponding QuickFixes or to do not execute those Change commands, but any other of the corresponding QuickFix.</p>
                        <note>
                            <p>Please note, that supporting any XPath 2.0/XSLT 2.0 functionality could have affects to the workflow: If one of the returned nodes changes the document context, the <titleref href="#workflow_fix_process">fix process</titleref> should respect this.</p>
                        </note>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="conditions">
                    <head>Conditions</head>
                    <p>Each change command can have a condition to execute. Therefore the attribute <att>use-when</att> is provided to each activity element. The condition will be defined in the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron errors</termref>. If the condition is not satisfied the change command should not be executed.</p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="fix_create_new_content">
                    <head>Create new content</head>
                    <p>Depending of the <titleref href="#change-command-kind">kind</titleref>, the change command may create new content to insert it into or replace nodes from the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref>. There are three ways to create new content:</p>
                    <div4 id="create-by-sqf-att">
                        <head>By the attributes <att>node-type</att> and <att>target</att></head>
                        <p>To create a new node, the change command may provide the attributes <att>node-type</att> and <att>target</att>. This attributes create exact one node.</p>
                        <p>To create a new node the attribute <att>node-type</att> provides the following values:<ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>keep</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create a node from the same type as the anchor node.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>element</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create an element.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>attribute</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create an attribute</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>processing-instruction</attval> or <attval>pi</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create a processing instruction</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>comment</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create a comment</p>
                                </item>
                            </ulist></p>
                        <p>Bellow a list of restrictions to use the node-type and target attribute:<ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>If the <att>node-type</att> attribute has not the value <attval>comment</attval>, the attribute <att>target</att> is required. It sets the name of the created node. The value of the <att>target</att> attribute will be interpreted as an <titleref href="#attribute-value-template">attribute value template</titleref>. The effective value should be valid to the XSD type xs:QName.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>If an Activity Element has a target attribute, the <att>node-type</att> attribute is required.</p>
                                </item>
                            </ulist></p>
                        <p>To create the value or content of the new node, you need to respect the following terms:<ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>If the <att>node-type</att> attribute has the value <attval>element</attval> (or <attval>keep</attval> and the anchor element is an element), the content of the new element will be created <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the Activity Element</titleref>.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>If the <att>node-type</att> attribute has the values <attval>attribute</attval>, <attval>processing-instruction</attval>, <attval>pi</attval> or <attval>comment</attval> (or <attval>keep</attval> and the anchor node is not an element), the value of the new node will be created <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the Activity Element</titleref>. If this returns nodes, the value will be created by the values of this nodes. More than one node value will be joined to one node value separated by whitespace.</p>
                                </item>
                            </ulist></p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="create-by-xpath">
                        <head>By an XPath expression</head>
                        <p>To define the new content by an XPath expression, the <att>select</att> attribute is provided. The select attribute can be combined with the attributes node-type and target. In this case the XPath expression of the select attribute detects the content or value of the new node. Otherwise the XPath expression creates new content in the following way:</p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>If the XPath expression returns an atomic value, the value will be transformed into an text node.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>If the XPath expression returns a sequence of atomic values, all values will be transformed to a text node. The values will be separated by whitespace.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>If the XPath expression returns one or more nodes, the nodes will be copied into the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref> (see below <titleref href="#copy-nodes">Copy nodes</titleref>). </p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                        <p>If the Activity Element has a <att>select</att> attribute, the element content should be empty.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="create-by-content">
                        <head>By the Activity Element content</head>
                        <p>The content of the Activity Elements has the same functionality as the content of <el>xsl:template</el> elements from the <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20">XSLT 2.0 Recommendation</titleref>. This means:</p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Elements from the XSLT namespace will be processed in the context of the change command. If XSLT elements are able to change the context in XSLT, this should have the same effect to there descendents in SQF.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Elements which not belong to the XSLT, SQF or Schematron namespace will be processed as <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#dt-literal-result-element">Literal Result Elements</titleref>.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                        <p>Extensions of the XSLT template behavior:</p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Elements from the SQF namespace will be processed as it is defined in this specification. Permitted element is:<ulist>
                                        <item>
                                            <p><el>sqf:copy-of</el></p>
                                            <p>To copy existing nodes into the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref> (see below <titleref href="#copy-nodes">Copy nodes</titleref>).</p>
                                        </item>
                                    </ulist></p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Elements from the Schematron namespace will be processed as it is defined in the Schematron specification. Permitted elements are:<ulist>
                                        <item>
                                            <p><el>sch:let</el></p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                            <p><el>sch:value-of</el></p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                            <p><el>sch:name</el></p>
                                        </item>
                                    </ulist></p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>The XSLT instruction <el>xsl:apply-templates</el> should be handled as if there is a copy templates defined (see below <titleref href="#copy-nodes">Copy nodes</titleref>).</p>
                        </item>
                        </ulist>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="copy-nodes">
                        <head>Copy nodes</head>
                        <p>There are three ways to copy nodes:</p>
                        <p>
                            <ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>If the XPath expression of the <att>select</att> attribute of an Activity Element returns one or more nodes, these nodes will be copied.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>With the <el>sqf:copy-of</el> element (as content of an Activity Element) nodes can be copied. A <att>select</att> attribute defines by an XPath expression the nodes to be copied. The default value of the <att>select</att> attribute is <attval>node()</attval>.</p>
                                </item>
                        <item>
                                    <p>If the XSLT instruction <el>xsl:apply-templates</el> is used as content of an Activity Element, the applied nodes should also be copied. The implementation is free to do a full copy of the applied nodes or to respect change commands caused by other (or the same) executed QuickFixes. (<titleref href="#example_apply_fixes">See example in Appendix</titleref>)</p>
                    </item>
                            </ulist>
                        </p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="conflicts">
                    <head>Conflicts</head>
                    <p>A conflict is thrown, if there are more than one change command for the same anchor node, during an QuickFix execution. There are two kinds of conflicts:<ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Resolvable conflict</p>
                                <p>If the conflict is between two or more change commands which belongs to the same QuickFix, the conflict is resolvable. In this case, the change command will be executed, whose activity element is defined at first inside of the <el>sqf:fix</el> element.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Warning raised conflict</p>
                                <p>If two or more change commands from different QuickFixes are in conflict, the conflict is not resolvable. A warning should be produced. The implementation is free to decide which QuickFix has higher priority. This kind of a conflict is just possible, if an implementation allows to execute more than one QuickFix at once.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist></p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="kind_of_the_change_commands">
                    <head id="change-command-kind">Kind of the change commands</head>
                    <p>There are four predefined kinds of change commands:<ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Add</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Delete</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Replace</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>StringReplace</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist></p>
                    <p>A Schematron QuickFix implementation is free to provide extending Change commands. The extending change commands should provide the attributes of the attribute group <titleref href="#sqf_activityBase"><phrase><code>activityBase</code></phrase></titleref> and respect the concepts to <titleref href="#fix_create_new_content">create new content</titleref>.</p>
                    <div4 id="add">
                        <head>Add</head>
                        <p>Creates one or more nodes and insert it relative to the anchor node as new content. The new content could be created by the <titleref href="#create-by-sqf-att">SQF attributes</titleref>, <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the sqf:add element</titleref>.</p>
                        <p>The position attribute detects the position relative to the anchor node, where the new content should be inserted. The following values are available:</p>
                        <p><glist>
                                <gitem>
                                    <label>first-child</label>
                                    <def>
                                        <p>If the anchor node is an element the new content will be inserted after the start tag of the anchor node.</p>
                                        <p>If the anchor node is an attribute, the new content will be inserted after the start tag of the parent element of the anchor node.</p>
                                        <p>Otherwise: the new content will be inserted after the anchor node.</p>
                                        <p>This value is the default value of the <att>position</att> attribute.</p>
                                    </def>
                                </gitem>
                                <gitem>
                                    <label>last-child</label>
                                    <def>
                                        <p>If the anchor node is an element the new content will be inserted before the end tag of the anchor node.</p>
                                        <p>If the anchor node is an attribute, the new content will be inserted before the end tag of the parent element of the anchor node.</p>
                                        <p>Otherwise: the new content will be inserted after the anchor node.</p>
                                    </def>
                                </gitem>
                                <gitem>
                                    <label>before</label>
                                    <def>
                                        <p>The new content will be inserted before the anchor node.</p>
                                        <p>If the anchor node is an attribute, the new content will be inserted before the parent element of the anchor node.</p>
                                    </def>
                                </gitem>
                                <gitem>
                                    <label>after</label>
                                    <def>
                                        <p>The new content will be inserted after the anchor node.</p>
                                        <p>If the anchor node is an attribute, the new content will be inserted after the parent element of the anchor node.</p>
                                    </def>
                                </gitem>
                            </glist></p>
                        <p>The <att>position</att> attribute is useless, if the new content are one or more attributes. In this case, the new content should always be added as attribute(s) of the anchor node.</p>
                        <p role="error-def">In the case, the new content is an attribute, it is an error if the anchor node is not an element.</p>
                        <p>If the anchor node is an element and has an attribute with the same name as one of the new attributes, the new attributes should replace the existing attributes.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="delete">
                        <head>Delete</head>
                        <p>This change command deletes the anchor node.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="replace">
                        <head>Replace</head>
                        <p>The anchor node will be replaced by new content. The new content can be created by the <titleref href="#create-by-sqf-att">SQF attributes</titleref>, <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the sqf:replace element</titleref>.</p>
                        <p role="error-def">It is an error, if the new content is an attribute, but the anchor node not.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="stringreplace">
                        <head>StringReplace</head>
                        <p>The anchor node has to be a text node. To analyze the text node, the <att>regex</att> attribute is required. The attribute value of the regex attribute will be interpreted as an <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#attribute-value-templates">attribute value template</titleref>. The effective value should be a valid <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#regular-expressions">Regular Expression</titleref> corresponding to the XSLT 2.0 Recommendation.</p>
                        <p>To control the interpretation of the Regular Expression, a <att>flag</att> attribute should be available. Also the given <att>flag</att> attribute value should be handled the same way as the XSLT 2.0 Recommendation handles the <att>flag</att> attribute of the <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#analyze-string">xsl:analyze-string instruction</titleref>.</p>
                        <p>Any substrings, which matches to this Regular Expression, will be replaced by new content. The new content can be created <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the sqf:stringReplace element</titleref>.</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="variables">
                <head>Variables</head>
                <div3 id="declaration">
                    <head>Declaration</head>
                    <p>The Schematron QuickFix specification does not provide an own structure to declare variables for the XPath expressions. There are two permitted ways do declare variables:</p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>Using Schematron variables (<el>sch:let</el>).</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Using XSLT variables (<el>xsl:variable</el>).</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>
                    <p>There is no difference between this ways, though the XSLT variables provides more functionality (e.g. <att>as</att> attribute, value by content). There should be no change of the original functionality by using these variable structures for Schematron QuickFix.</p>
                    <div4 id="places_to_declare_variables">
                        <head>Places to declare variables</head>
                        <p>There are two places (inside of the SQF elements) to declare variables:</p>
                        <p><ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>In a <el>sqf:fix</el> element</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Inside of any activity element.</p>
                                </item>
                            </ulist>
                        </p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="scope">
                        <head>Scope</head>
                        <p>There should be no changes to the original scope behavior of the used variable concepts.</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="usage">
                    <head>Usage</head>
                    <p>Variables should be available in any XPath expressions, which are in the scope of the variable. This shall also apply to the variables which are declared outside of the Schematron QuickFix elements (global variables or variables in <el>sch:rule</el> elements).</p>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="parameter">
                <head>Parameter</head>
                <p>There are two different ways to use parameters for QuickFixes:</p>
                <p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p><emph>Default parameter:</emph> The default parameter is a common parameter to reuse and parametrize the QuickFix. Therefore the reused QuickFix may contains parameter(s) (see chapter <titleref href="#param.declaration">Declaration</titleref>). Another QuickFix may call the reused QuickFix (see chapter <titleref href="#param.call-fix">Call a QuickFix</titleref>). During the call, the calling QuickFix is able to set the value of the parameters of the reused QuickFix. </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p><emph>Abstract parameter:</emph> This parameter is to declare the usage of Schematron parameters inside of the QuickFix, which should be defined by the <el>sch:param</el> element.</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>
                </p>
                <p>The following sections should discuss the default parameter. The abstract parameter will be discussed in the section <titleref href="#abstract-param">Abstract parameter</titleref> only.</p>
                <div3 id="param.declaration">
                    <head>Declaration</head>
                    <p>The declaration of a parameter has to be at the beginning of the <el>sqf:fix</el> element, before any other elements. The sqf:param element declares one parameter. To declare multiple parameter you need multiple <el>sqf:param</el> elements.</p>
                    <div4 id="name">
                        <head>Name</head>
                        <p>The <att>name</att> attribute is the only required attribute of the <el>sqf:param</el> element. It sets the name of the parameter.</p>
                        <p role="error-def">It is an error, if there is an other parameter inside of the <el>sqf:fix</el> element with the same name.</p>
                        <p>The value of the name attribute should to be valid to the type xs:QName.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="param.default-value">
                        <head>Default value</head>
                        <p>The default value of the parameter will be set by the <att>default</att> attribute. The attribute value needs to be a valid XPath expression. The parameter will have the returned value, if the value is not set by the call of this fix (see chapter <titleref href="#param.call-fix">Call a QuickFix</titleref>). </p>
                        <p>If the <att>default</att> attribute is omitted, the default value is a zero length string. </p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="type">
                        <head>Type</head>
                        <p>If the <att>type</att> attribute is set, it specifies the required type of the parameter value. If the <att>type</att> attribute is omitted, the type of the parameter value is unspecified. The implementation is free to support proprietary or a standardised types. The types needs to be referred by a valid xs:QName.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="required_parameters">
                        <head>Required parameters</head>
                        <p>A parameter is by default optional. If the call-fix do not specify a value for an optional parameter, the <titleref href="param.default-value">default value</titleref> will be used. The required attribute with the value <attval>yes</attval> indicates that the parameter value needs to be specified by the call-fix. </p>
                        <p role="error-def">It is an error, if the <att>default</att> attribute is not omitted, though the <att>required</att> attribute has the value <attval>yes</attval>.</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="param.call-fix">
                    <head>Call a QuickFix</head>
                    <p>There are different use cases to call a QuickFix. In any case the <el>sqf:call-fix</el> element should be used:</p>
                    <p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Reuse the change commands of one QuickFix, specified by parameters.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Combine the change commands of QuickFixes by multiple QuickFix calls.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Add specific change commands to a QuickFix by mixing Activity Elements with one or more QuickFix calls.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Specify a description(s) to the called QuickFixes or reuse the description of the called QuickFix.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                    </p>
                            <p>All use cases could be combined as well. If a QuickFix has multiple QuickFix calls or a mix of one QuickFix call and one or more Activity Elements, a specific descriptions (sqf:description element) is mandatory. The reuse of the description of a called QuickFix is only permitted, if the calling QuickFix contains exactly one QuickFix call.</p>
                    <p>To call a QuickFix, the <el>sqf:fix</el> element of the calling QuickFix may contain a <el>sqf:call-fix</el> element at any position. The only condition is, that it is after any <el>sqf:param</el> and <el>sqf:description</el> elements. The <el>sqf:call-fix</el> element should have a mandatory <att>ref</att> attribute. Its value should refer to an ID of any available QuickFix. The referred QuickFix will be called.</p>
                    <p>If the calling QuickFix is a <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">global</titleref> QuickFix, only other <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">global</titleref> QuickFixes or QuickFixes of <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">global</titleref>
                        <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix groups</titleref> are available. If the calling QuickFix is <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">local</titleref>, any QuickFix is available, which is available for any assertion in the scope of the calling QuickFix. Additionally if there is a <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">local</titleref> QuickFix which has the same ID as a <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">global</titleref> QuickFix, the <titleref href="#quick-fix.global-local">local</titleref> QuickFix may refer to the global QuickFix by containing a <el>sqf:call-fix</el> element with a <att>ref</att> attribute which refers to the ID of it self.</p>
                    <p>It is permitted, to call a QuickFix inside of a <titleref href="#generic-fixes">generic QuickFix</titleref>.</p>
                    <p>It should be occured an error, if the called QuickFix is a <titleref href="#generic-fixes">generic QuickFix</titleref>.</p>
                    <div4 id="specify_a_parameter">
                        <head>Specify a parameter</head>
                        <p>A <el>sqf:call-fix</el> element may contain one or more <el>sqf:with-param</el> elements. Each <el>sqf:with-param</el> element set a value of one parameter of the called QuickFix. The mandatory <att>name</att> attribute determines which parameter of the called QuickFix will be specified. The type of the <att>name</att> attribute needs to be a valid xs:QName.</p>
                        <p>It is mandatory, that in the called QuickFix a parameter is declared which have the same name as the <att>name</att> attribute of the <el>sqf:with-param</el> element. </p>
                        <p>The value of the parameter will be defined the same way as the <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#variable-values">values of XSLT 2.0 variables or parameters</titleref>, though it is no <att>as</att> attribute available.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="adoption_of_properties">
                        <head>Adoption of properties</head>
                        <p>If a QuickFix calls another QuickFix, the calling QuickFix will adopt some kind of properties in any case, some properties only if there is no property from the same kind set for the calling QuickFix and other properties will be never adopted. If a QuickFix adopt a property, it is, as if the calling QuickFix obtained this property by itself. If the order of the property elements is significant (for instance the order of the activity elements), the effective position will be determinated by replacing all <el>sqf:call-fix</el> elements by the adopted property elements.</p>
                        <p>The following properties of the called QuickFix will be adopted in any case:<ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Any change command (defined by Activity Elements)</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>User Entry to parametrise the QuickFix (see <titleref href="#user-entry">User Entries</titleref>)</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Any other property of the above kinds, which may be adopted by another QuickFix call.</p>
                                </item>
                            </ulist></p>
                        <p>The following properties will be adopted conditionally:<ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Description:: title and additional documentation</p>
                                    <p>An adoption of the description is permitted only, if the calling QuickFix calls exactly one QuickFix and does not contains any Activity Element. Otherwise a specific description for the calling QuickFix is mandatory.</p>
                                    <p>The descriptions of the called QuickFix will be adopted, if the calling QuickFix has no description from the same language. If the calling QuickFix has a description in a specific language, but the called QuickFix has or adopt multiple descriptions, the calling QuickFix adopts all descriptions which has a different language, then its own description(s) (see also <titleref href="#localization">Localisation</titleref>).</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Condition to provide the QuickFix</p>
                                <p>The condition to provide will be adopted only, if the calling QuickFix calls exactly one QuickFix, does not contain any Activity Element and has no specific <att>use-when</att> attribute.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Any other property of the above kinds, which may be adopted by another QuickFix call and satisfies the conditions described above.</p>
                                </item>
                            </ulist></p>
                        <p>The following properties will not be adopted in any case:<ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>ID</p>
                                </item>
                                </ulist></p>
                        <p>It is an error, if the called QuickFix has the following property:<ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p>Loop to make the QuickFix generic (see <titleref href="#generic-fixes">Generic QuickFix</titleref>)</p>
                                </item>
                            </ulist></p>
                        <note>
                            <p>Please note, that it is permitted, to call a QuickFix inside of a generic QuickFix.</p>
                    </note>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="example">
                    <head>Example</head>
                    <p><example>
                            <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sqf:fix id="call-fix"> 
    [...] 
    &lt;sqf:call-fix ref="reused-fix"> 
        &lt;sqf:with-param name="param1" select="10"/> 
    &lt;/sqf:call-fix> 
&lt;/sqf:fix> 
&lt;sqf:fix id="reused-fix"> 
    &lt;sqf:param name="param1" default="'defaultValue'" type="xs:string"/> 
    &lt;sqf:param name="param2" required="yes" type="xs:integer"/> 
    [...] 
&lt;/sqf:fix></eg>
                        </example></p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="abstract-param">
                    <head>Abstract parameter</head>
                    <div4 id="abstract_parameter_declaration">
                        <head>Declaration</head>
                        <p>A <titleref href="#sqf_param">sch:param</titleref> element from a QuickFix with the value of the <att>abstract</att> attribute set to <attval>true</attval> is defined as an abstract parameter of the QuickFix. As the <titleref href="#parameter">default parameter</titleref>, the abstract parameter declaration must be at the beginning of an <el>sqf:fix</el> element.</p>
                        <p>A QuickFix referred from an abstract pattern must declare all abstract pattern parameters used by it. A <titleref href="#sqf_with-param">sch:param</titleref> element, with the value of the <att>abstract</att> attribute set to <attval>true</attval>, must be added for all abstract pattern parameters used in the QuickFix.</p>
                        <p>An abstract parameter defined in a QuickFix declares that the QuickFix uses a parameter of an abstract pattern. The QuickFix can be instantiate only from an abstract pattern that defines the abstract parameter. A QuickFix with one or more abstract parameters can be used only from abstract patterns. </p>
                        <p>If a QuickFix <titleref href="#parameter">parameter</titleref> that is defined as abstract it cannot have the <att>type</att>, <att>required</att> and <att>default</att> attributes. Its value will be set form the abstract pattern instantiation.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="abstract_parameter_usage">
                        <head>Usage</head>
                        <p>Abstract parameters cannot be used as normal XPath variables. The reference of the abstract parameter will be replaced at instantiation by the value specified in the abstract pattern. The replacing value will be set by the instantiation of the abstract pattern according to the <titleref href="http://www.schematron.com/iso/P8.html#GEN11">Schematron specification</titleref>. The instantiation of the abstract pattern must specify a value for every abstract parameter of the QuickFix.</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="user_entry">
                <head>User Entry</head>
                <p>A User Entry is a parameter for the QuickFix which can be set by the user during the runtime of the QuickFix execution. </p>
                <p>A QuickFix can have multiple User Entries. A User Entry requires the following properties:</p>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Title: A short description of the functionality of the User Entry</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Name: To refer the User Entry value inside of the XPath expressions of the QuickFix</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist>
                <p>A User Entry is able to have the following additional properties:</p>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Descriptions: More documentation information.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Default value: To suggest this value to the user.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Type: To restrict the possible values of the User Entry and get the value in the correct data type </p>
                    </item>
                </ulist>
                <div3 id="definition_of_a_user_entry">
                    <head>Definition of a User Entry</head>
                    <p>User Entries have to be defined before any change commands in the <el>sqf:fix</el> element:</p>
                    <p><example>
                            <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sqf:fix id="fix1">
    &lt;sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:title>Fix 1&lt;/sqf:title>
    &lt;/sqf:description>
    &lt;sqf:user-entry name="ue1">
        &lt;sqf:description>
            &lt;sqf:title>User Entry 1&lt;/sqf:title>
        &lt;/sqf:description>
    &lt;/sqf:user-entry>
    &lt;sqf:user-entry name="ue2">
        &lt;sqf:description>
            &lt;sqf:title>User Entry 2&lt;/sqf:title>
        &lt;/sqf:description>
    &lt;/sqf:user-entry>
    [Elements from the content model  (sqf:delete | sqf:add | sqf:replace | sqf:stringReplace)+]
&lt;/sqf:fix></eg>
                        </example></p>
                    <p>Each <el>sqf:user-entry</el> element defines an User Entry. Consequently, the QuickFix <code>fix1</code> has two User Entries with the names <code>ue1</code> and <code>ue2</code>.</p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="value_usage">
                    <head>Value usage</head>
                    <p>To use the value, each User Entry can be used as an XPath variable. So the value of the User Entry can be used in each XPath expression of all Activity Elements in the User Entry. The name of the XPath variable is the name of User Entry.</p>
                    <p><example>
                            <eg>&lt;sqf:user-entry name="ue1"> 
    &lt;sqf:description> 
        &lt;sqf:title>User Entry 1&lt;/sqf:title>
      &lt;/sqf:description>
 &lt;/sqf:user-entry>
 &lt;sqf:replace target="{$ue1}" node-type="element" select="$ue1"/></eg>
                        </example></p>
                    <p>The Activity Element <el>sqf:replace</el> replaces the anchor node (<termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron errors</termref>) by a new element. The name will be set by the user by setting the User Entry <code>ue1</code>. The content of the new element will be also the value of the User Entry <code>ue1</code>. </p>
                    <div4 id="user_entry_scope">
                        <head>Scope</head>
                        <p>The User Entry value is available in all XPath expressions of all Activity Elements of the QuickFix. </p>
                        <p><emph>Exceptions:</emph></p>
                        <p>There could some restrictions of the implementation, which could restrict this (for instance, <titleref href="#anchor_node_restrictions">restrictions to the match attribute</titleref>).</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="implementation_of_user_entries">
                    <head>Implementation of User Entries</head>
                    <p>A SQF implementation which supports User Entries should provide the user an interface to set User Entries after or while choosing the QuickFix. For this the titles of each User Entry should be displayed in connection with the corresponding QuickFixes.</p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="default_value">
                    <head>Default value</head>
                    <p>The default attribute sets a default value for the User Entry, using an XPath expression. The result value can be used by the implementation to provide a default value to the user, when he set the User Entry. The default value should used like the default value of a parameter (see <el>sqf:param</el> element): </p>
                    <ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>There are no optional User Entries.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Each User Entry should be set by the user.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>The default value is to provide it as possible value only.</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="embedding_xpath">
                <head>Embedding XPath</head>
                <p>Schematron QuickFix is based on the W3C Recommendation XPath 2.0. Any XPath expression of the Schematron schema needs to match the syntax allowed by the XPath grammar.</p>
                <div3 id="attributes_to_embed_xpath_expressions">
                    <head>Attributes to embed XPath expressions</head>
                    <p>The following table shows attributes, whose value will be parsed as XPath expressions, corresponding to the <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath20/">XPath 2.0</titleref> Recommendation:</p>
                    <p>
                        <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2">
                            <thead>
                                <tr>
                                    <th>Attribute</th>
                                    <th>Element</th>
                                    <th>Context</th>
                                    <th>Description</th>
                                    <th>Required return type</th>
                                </tr>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="2">default</td>
                                    <td>sqf:param</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Default value for the parameter</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:user-entry</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Default value for the User Entry</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="4">match</td>
                                    <td>sqf:add</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Contexts of the change commands</td>
                                    <td>node()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:delete</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Contexts of the change commands</td>
                                    <td>node()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:replace</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Contexts of the change commands</td>
                                    <td>node()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:stringReplace</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Contexts of the change commands</td>
                                    <td>text()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="5">select</td>
                                    <td>sqf:add</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Nodes or atomic values, which should be inserted</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:copy-of</td>
                                    <td>Inherits from the parent node.</td>
                                    <td>Nodes to copy</td>
                                    <td>node()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:replace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Nodes or atomic values, which should be inserted</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:stringReplace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Nodes or atomic values, which should be inserted</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:with-param</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Value for the parameter</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="6">use-when</td>
                                    <td>sqf:add</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to process the change command</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:delete</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to process the change command</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:replace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to process the change command</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:stringReplace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to process the change command</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:fix</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to provide the QuickFix</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:group</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to provide all QuickFixes of this <titleref href="#quick-fix.group">QuickFix group</titleref></td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="attribute-value-template">
                    <head>Attribute Value Template</head>
                    <p>The following table shows attributes, whose value is interpreted as <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#attribute-value-templates">attribute value template</titleref> corresponding to the XSLT 2.0 Recommendation:</p>
                    <p>
                        <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2">
                            <thead>
                                <tr>
                                    <th>Attribute</th>
                                    <th>Element</th>
                                    <th>Context</th>
                                    <th>Effective value requirements</th>
                                </tr>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>regex</td>
                                    <td>sqf:stringReplace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Valid <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#regular-expressions">Regular Expression</titleref> corresponding to the XSLT 2.0 Recommendation.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="2">target</td>
                                    <td>sqf:add</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>xs:QName</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:replace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>xs:QName</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>The effective value requirements should be satisfied after interpreting the attribute value template.</p>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="localization">
                <head>Localization</head>
                <p>The SQF localisation concept is based on the <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/#sec-lang-tag">XML concept to detect the natural language</titleref>, using the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute. Consequently, SQF elements are able to inherit the language property of all ancestors.</p>
                <div3 id="locatable_elements">
                    <head>Locatable elements</head>
                    <p>The following list shows SQF elements, which are locatable with the attribute <att>xml:lang</att>:</p>
                    <p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p><el>sqf:description</el></p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><el>sqf:fix</el></p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><el>sqf:fixes</el></p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><el>sqf:group</el></p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><el>sqf:user-entry</el></p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                    </p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="localisation_of_a_quickfix">
                    <head>Localisation of a QuickFix</head>
                    <p>To define multiple descriptions for one QuickFix, but in different languages, the <el>sqf:fix</el> element is permitted to contain multiple <el>sqf:description</el> elements. It is restricted, that a <el>sqf:fix</el> element should not contain two <el>sqf:description</el> elements with the same <att>xml:lang</att> attribute value (or both with no <att>xml:lang</att> attribute).</p>
                    <p>In case there are multiple <el>sqf:description</el> elements, the first <el>sqf:description</el> should be the default description. In case the implementation does not support the localisation or there is no language given, it should use this default description.</p>
                    <div4>
                        <head>Localisation using QuickFix calls</head>
                        <p>The section <titleref href="#param.call-fix">Call a QuickFix</titleref> describes, that the calling QuickFix is able to adopts the property Description (title and additional documentation) of the called QuickFix conditionally, depending on the language.</p>
                        <p>One use case of a QuickFix call is, to localize existing QuickFixes. If an existing QuickFix should localize, because it has a description in only one language or a description for a language is missing, the QuickFix could be called by a new calling QuickFix. The calling QuickFix may specify - beside the QuickFix call - only additional descriptions in the missing languages. The calling QuickFix will adopt all change commands of the existing QuickFix and all descriptions, if the calling QuickFix does not contain any in the same language. Additionally the calling QuickFIx is so able to specify descriptions for different languages.</p>
                </div4>
                </div3>
            </div2>
        </div1>
        <div1 id="implementation_modes">
            <head>Implementation modes</head>
            <p>A QuickFix can be implemented generally in two different modes:<ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Unparsed Process Mode</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>XSLT only mode</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist></p>
            <p>An implementation is free to support only one or both modes. If a implementation supports both modes, it should be a general configurarion to switch between the two modes.</p>
            <div2 id="xml_save_mode">
                <head>Unparsed Process Mode</head>
                <p>The Unparsed Process Mode requires that no changes will be applied to the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref>, which are not defined by the executed QuickFix. Changes which are caused by parsing the document and creating a new, XML identical document (skip the XML declaration, resolving default attributes, CDATA sections, etc.), should not influence the document. That is why it is not possible to implement the Unparsed Process Mode with only XSLT processes.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="xslt_only_mode">
                <head>XSLT only mode</head>
                <p>If an implementation is based only on XSLT processes, this is called the XSLT only mode. In this case, it is allowed to change the <termref def="sch-source-document">source document</termref> on any QuickFix execution in the following ways, though it is not defined in the QuickFix:<ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>Skip the XML declaration</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Skip the DOCTYPE declaration</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Skip whitespace:<ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>which are outside of the root element and not in processing instructions and comments.</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>non significant whitespace</p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist></p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Normalize whitespace<ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>Leading whitespace of content in processing instructions in prolog</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>between attributes</p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist></p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Resolve default attributes to encoded attributes</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Resolve CDATA sections to text nodes.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Resolve entity references.</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist></p>
            </div2>
        </div1>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="SQFSpec_Elements.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
                <div1>
                    <head>No reference available</head>
                </div1>
            </xi:fallback>
        </xi:include>
    </body>
    <back>
        <div1 id="schematron_quick_fixes_schema">
            <head>Schematron Quick Fixes schema</head>
            <eg><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schemas/schematron-quickFix.xsd" parse="text"/></eg>
        </div1>
        <div1 id="examples">
            <head>Examples</head>
            <div2 id="example_external_doc">
                <head>QuickFixes for external documents</head>
                <p>A QuickFix can be applied also over other documents than the one where the fix is executed. Therefore, external documents can be modified using a QuickFix operations.</p>
                <p>There are two types of external documents:<ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>Documents referred with XInclude and external entities. You can access them as the nodes in the current document, as in the following example: </p>
                            <example>
                                <p>Main document on which the quick if is applied:</p>
                                <eg>&lt;Root xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    &lt;xi:include href="included.xml"/>
    &lt;Element>2&lt;/Element>
&lt;/Root></eg>
                                <p>Included document <quote>included.xml</quote>:</p>
                                <eg>&lt;Element>3&lt;/Element></eg>
                                <p>QuickFix that modifies the value of the element from the XIncluded file.</p>
                                <eg>&lt;sch:rule context="Element[preceding-sibling::Element]">
    &lt;sch:assert test="number(.) > number(preceding-sibling::Element[1])" sqf:fix="AdjustPrevValue">
        The current element value should be greater then the previous value.
    &lt;/sch:assert>
    
    &lt;sqf:fix id="AdjustPrevValue">
        &lt;sch:let name="NewValue" value="number(.) - 1"/>
        &lt;sqf:description>
            &lt;sqf:title>Adjust previous value to &lt;sch:value-of select="$NewValue"/>&lt;/sqf:title>
        &lt;/sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:replace match="preceding-sibling::Element[1]/text()" select="$NewValue"/>
    &lt;/sqf:fix>
&lt;/sch:rule></eg>
                            </example>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Documents referred using other type of references. You can apply the quick fixes over other documents using the <function>doc()</function> function in the value of the <att>match</att> attribute. For example, you can add a new key in the <code>keylist.xml</code> file using the following operation:</p>
                            <example>
                                <eg>&lt;sqf:add match="doc('keylist.xml')/KeyList" target="Key" node-type="element" select="Key2"></eg>
                            </example>
                        </item>
                    </ulist></p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="formatting_and_indenting_inserted_content">
                <head>Formatting and Indenting Inserted Content</head>
                <p>The content that is inserted by the Add, Replace, or String Replace operations can be formatted. There are several methods available to format the content that is inserted:<ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p><term>xsl:text</term> - You can use an <el>xsl:text</el> element to format the inserted content, as in the following example:<example>
                                    <eg>&lt;sqf:add position="last-child">
    &lt;row>&lt;xsl:text>
    &lt;/xsl:text>
        &lt;entry>First column&lt;/entry>&lt;xsl:text>
        &lt;/xsl:text>
        &lt;entry>Second column&lt;/entry>&lt;xsl:text>
        &lt;/xsl:text>
    &lt;/row>&lt;xsl:text>
    &lt;/xsl:text>
&lt;/sqf:add></eg>
                                </example></p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p><term>xml:space</term> - Use the <att>xml:space</att> attribute and set its value to <attval>preserve</attval> to format the content and specify the spacing between elements, as in the following example:<example>
                                    <eg>&lt;sqf:add node-type="element" target="codeblock" xml:space="preserve">
    /* a long sample program */
    Do forever
     Say "Hello, World"
    End&lt;/sqf:add></eg>
                                </example></p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist></p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="example_apply_fixes" role="unfinished">
                <head>QuickFix which applies to itself</head>
                <p>Tbd.</p>
            </div2>
        </div1>
    </back>
</spec>
