<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.w3.org/XML/1998/06/schema/xmlspec.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<spec>
    <header>
        <title>Schematron Quick Fixes Specification</title>
        <w3c-designation>W3C Designation</w3c-designation>
        <w3c-doctype>Quick-fix support for XML Community Group - Draft</w3c-doctype>
        <pubdate>
            <month>April</month>
            <year>2015</year>
        </pubdate>
        <publoc>
            <loc href="http://schematron-quickfix.github.io/sqf/spec/SQFSpec.html">schematron-quickfix.github.io/sqf/spec/SQFSpec.html</loc>
        </publoc>
        <latestloc>
            <loc href="http://schematron-quickfix.github.io/sqf/spec/SQFSpec.html">schematron-quickfix.github.io/sqf/spec/SQFSpec.html</loc>
        </latestloc>
        <authlist>
            <author>
                <name>Nico Kutscherauer</name>
            </author>
            <author>
                <name>Octavian Nadolu</name>
            </author>
        </authlist>
        <copyright>
            <p>Copyright © 2015, published by the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/quickfix/">Quick-fix support for XML Community Group</loc> under the <xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla/">W3C Community Contributor License Agreement (CLA)</xspecref>. A human-readable <xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla-deed/">summary</xspecref> is available. </p>
        </copyright>
        <status>
            <p><emph>This specification was published by the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/quickfix/">Quick-fix support for XML Community Group</loc>. It is not a W3C Standard nor is it on the W3C Standards Track. Please note that under the <xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/community/about/agreements/cla/">W3C Community Contributor License Agreement (CLA)</xspecref> there is a limited opt-out and other conditions apply. Learn more about <loc href="http://www.w3.org/community/">W3C Community and Business Groups</loc>.</emph></p>
            <p>First Draft</p>
        </status>
        <abstract>
            <p>Schematron QuickFix is an extension of the ISO standard Schematron. With Schematron QuickFix the developer is able to define QuickFixes for the Schematron errors. The implementation should offer the user these QuickFixes for the reported Schematron errors. With just one click the user can decide which QuickFix acceptably fixes the error.</p>
        </abstract>
        <langusage>
            <language>English</language>
        </langusage>
        <revisiondesc>
            <p>Revision description</p>
        </revisiondesc>
    </header>
    <body>
        <div1>
            <head>Namespaces and prefixes</head>
            <p>This document describes the nodes which belong to different namespaces. For distinction and for unique descriptions all nodes, which do not belong to the NULL namespace, are named with a prefix. The following table assigns to each used prefix the corresponding namespace URI:</p>
            <table>
                <thead>
                    <tr>
                        <th>Prefix</th>
                        <th>Namespace URI</th>
                        <th>Corresponding standard</th>
                    </tr>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <tr>
                        <td>sch</td>
                        <td>http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron</td>
                        <td>ISO Schematron</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>sqf</td>
                        <td>http://www.schematron-quickfix.com/validator/process</td>
                        <td>Schematron QuickFix</td>
                    </tr>
                    <tr>
                        <td>xsl</td>
                        <td>http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform</td>
                        <td>XSLT 2.0</td>
                    </tr>
                </tbody>
            </table>
        </div1>
        <div1>
            <head>Terminology</head>
            <glist>
                <gitem>
                    <label id="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</label>
                    <def>
                        <p>Condition which is declared by the Schematron elements <el>sch:report</el> or <el>sch:assert</el>.</p>
                        <p>A failed Schematron assertion produces a <termref def="sch-error">Schematron error</termref>. One Schematron assertion can produce multiple <termref def="sch-error">Schematron errors</termref>. </p>
                    </def>
                </gitem>
                <gitem>
                    <label id="sch-rule">Schematron rule</label>
                    <def>
                        <p>According to the Schematron element <el>sch:rule</el>. It contains one or more <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertions</termref>.</p>
                        <glist>
                            <gitem id="sch-rule-context">
                                <label>Context</label>
                                <def>
                                    <p>The context of a <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rule</termref> is defined by the attribute <att>context</att>. If a rule matches to more than one node, it has more than one context. </p>
                                </def>
                            </gitem>
                        </glist>
                    </def>
                </gitem>
                <gitem>
                    <label id="sch-error">Schematron error</label>
                    <def>
                        <p>A Schematron error occurs if a <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref> failed.</p>
                        <glist>
                            <gitem>
                                <label id="sch-error-context">Context</label>
                                <def>
                                    <p>The context of the <termref def="sch-error">Schematron error</termref> is the node, which was matched by the Schematron rule, when the <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref> failed.</p>
                                    <p>The attribute <att>subject</att> has no affect to the context of the Schematron error. Unlike to the <termref def="sch-rule-context">context of the Schematron rule</termref>, the Schematron error has only one context node.</p>
                                </def>
                            </gitem>
                        </glist>
                    </def>
                </gitem>

            </glist>
        </div1>
        <div1>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>This section describes the classification of the based concepts of Schematron QuickFix.</p>
            <div2>
                <head>Fix</head>
                <p>A fix is a change of a document, applied to an occurred error. All changes must have the object to solve this error. Requirement is to detect the error first.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="quick-fix-concept">
                <head>Quick fix</head>
                <p>A Quick fix is a fully automatic implemented fix. In connection with an error (produced by a validation of a document) one ore more Quick fixes are offered to execute. A user can choose the Quick fix, which is executed by a fully automated process. </p>
                <p>A Quick fix requires: </p>
                <olist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Instructions, written in a document processing language, to implement the fix. The instructions have to designed in a way, that it is able to process them applied to a context. The context is defined by the occurred error.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>A human-readable description of the Quick fix. The description should be displayed to the user, when he chooses the Quick fix.</p>
                    </item>
                </olist>
                <p>It is able to define Quick fixes inside of a validation parser or using a therefore designed script language. First, there is a limited quantity of Quick fixes, in the second case the quantity is unlimited.</p>
                <p>It depends on the quantity of unique kinds of errors from the validation language, which way makes more sense. Is the quantity of kinds of errors limited, an implementation of Quick fixes inside of the parser is possible.</p>
                <p>Requirements:</p>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Links to or embedding into the parser or a validation language.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>A workflow to execute the Quick fixes.</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Graphical user interface to choose the Quick fixes.</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist>
            </div2>
        </div1>
        <div1>
            <head>Workflow</head>
            <p>Schematron QuickFix (SQF) is an extension of the validation language Schematron to embed Quick fixes. To overview the Schematron QuickFix concept, this section describes the integration of SQF into the Schematron workflow.</p>
            <p>The following figure shows the SQF workflow in eight steps:</p>
            <graphic source="img/workflow.png"/>
            <p>The following sections describes each step of the workflow diagram and its difference to the conventional Schematron workflow.</p>
            <div2>
                <head>Schematron validation</head>
                <glist>
                    <gitem>
                        <label id="sch-document">Document to be fixed</label>
                        <def>
                            <p/>
                        </def>
                    </gitem>
                </glist>
                
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Validation result</head>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Error report</head>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Show the errors in the document to be fixed</head>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Decision of the user</head>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Executing a Quick fix</head>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Validation after the fix</head>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Fixed document</head>
            </div2>
        </div1>
        <div1>
            <head>Language</head>
            <p>This section describes the meanings of the Schematron QuickFix syntax.</p>
            <div2>
                <head>Embedding into Schematron</head>
                <p>To embed Schematron QuickFix into Schematron, all extending elements should have the namespace <code>http://www.schematron-quickfix.com/validator/process</code> (prefix <code>sqf</code>).</p>
                <p>The following table shows the permitted parent-child relations between the namespaces of SQF and Schematron.</p>
                <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="10">
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Parent element</th>
                            <th>Permitted children</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sch:schema</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sqf:fixes</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sch:rule</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sqf:fix</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sqf:group</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:title</el>
                            </td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:name</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:value-of</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:p</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:name</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:value-of</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:emph</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:dir</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:span</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:fix</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><el>sch:let</el></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
                <p>The following table shows which attributes from the SQF namespace should be permitted of which Schematron elements:</p>
                <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="10">
                    <thead>
                        <tr>
                            <th>Schematron element</th>
                            <th>Permitted SQF attribute</th>
                        </tr>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:assert</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><att>sqf:fix</att></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><att>sqf:default-fix</att></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                        <tr>
                            <td><el>sqf:report</el></td>
                            <td>
                                <ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><att>sqf:fix</att></p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p><att>sqf:default-fix</att></p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist>
                            </td>
                        </tr>
                    </tbody>
                </table>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>QuickFix</head>
                <note>
                    <p>Please note the different spelling of <emph>QuickFix</emph> and <emph>Quick fix</emph>. The spelling QuickFix means a Quick fix of the extension language Schematron QuickFix. The spelling Quick fix means a not specific Quick fix, which was described in the section <titleref href="#quick-fix-concept">Quick fix</titleref>.</p>
                </note>
                <p>A QuickFix is consequently a <titleref href="#quick-fix-concept">Quick fix</titleref> of the language Schematron QuickFix.</p>
                <p>A QuickFix requires the following properties:</p>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Title</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>ID</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>One or more change commands (see <titleref href="#change-commands">Change commands</titleref>)</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist>
                <p>A QuickFix is able to have the following additional properties:</p>
                <ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>Additional description</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>Condition to provide the QuickFix</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>User Entry to parametrise the QuickFix (see <titleref href="#user-entry">User Entries</titleref>)</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist>
                <div3>
                    <head>Definition of a QuickFix</head>
                    <p>The QuickFix is defined by the <el>sqf:fix</el> element. The requirements will be satisfied with the following base structure:</p>
                    <p><example>
                            <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sqf:fix id="fix1">
    &lt;sqf:description>
        &lt;sqf:title>Fix 1&lt;/sqf:title>
    &lt;/sqf:description>
    [Elements from the content model  (sqf:delete | sqf:add | sqf:replace | sqf:stringReplace)+]
&lt;/sqf:fix></eg>
                        </example></p>
                    <p>The defined QuickFix above has the following properties:</p>
                    <p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Title: Fix 1</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>ID: fix1</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>One or more change commands: not specified yet.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                    </p>
                </div3>
                <div3>
                    <head>QuickFixes ID</head>
                    <p>The ID of the QuickFix and the QuickFix groups (see below) is the Identifier for references to QuickFixes and QuickFix groups.</p>
                    <p>Requirements to set the ID:<ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>The ID has to correspond with the XSD type xs:NCName.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Inside of a <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rule</termref> the ID must be unique.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Global QuickFixes or QuickFix groups should not have the same IDs.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist></p>
                    <p>In the following cases it is permitted that two QuickFixes, QuickFix groups or a QuickFix and a QuickFix group have the same IDs:<ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>One is global the other is local.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Both are local and declared in different <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rules</termref>.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist></p>
                </div3>
                <div3>
                    <head>Reference to a QuickFix</head>
                    <p><termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertions</termref> are able to refer to one or more QuickFixes. Therefore the <att>sqf:fix</att> attribute contains a whitespace separated list of IDs. Each ID refers to an ID of a QuickFix.</p>
                    <example>
                        <p>The <el>sch:assert</el> element refers to the QuickFixes with the ID <attval>fix1</attval> and <attval>fix2</attval>:</p>
                        <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sch:assert test="[...]" sqf:fix="fix1 fix2">[...]&lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;sqf:fix id="fix1"> 
    [...] 
&lt;/sqf:fix> 
&lt;sqf:fix id="fix2">
    [...] 
&lt;/sqf:fix></eg>
                    </example>
                    <p>Is a <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref> producing a <termref def="sch-error">Schematron error</termref> that refers to a QuickFix, a Schematron QuickFix implementation needs to provide the QuickFix as a choice for the user in connection to the occurred error.</p>
                    <p><emph>Exception:</emph> A QuickFix, which condition was not satisfied in the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref>, should not be provided.</p>
                    <p>The user should be able to execute each provided QuickFix.</p>
                </div3>
                <div3>
                    <head>Execution of a QuickFix</head>
                    <p>During the execution process of a QuickFix each <titleref href="#change-commands">command changes</titleref> will be executed in the <termref def="sch-error-context">context node of the error</termref>, if their condition was satisfied in this context.</p>
                    <div4>
                        <head>Execution of more than one QuickFix</head>
                        <p>It is free to the implementation to allow executions of more than one QuickFix at once. But a execution of more than one QuickFix of the same Schematron error at once are not permitted.</p>
                        <p>It is up to the implementation to warn the user against <titleref href="#conflicts">possible conflicts</titleref> or to hide QuickFixes to avoid such conflicts.</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3>
                    <head>QuickFix group</head>
                    <p>A QuickFix group is a set of one or more QuickFixes. Additional it needs an ID, which is equal to the ID of a QuickFix. The QuickFix will be implemented with the <el>sqf:group</el> element.</p>
                    <p>A <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertion</termref> is able to refer to a QuickFix group on the same way it refers to a QuickFix. A reference to a QuickFix groups is equal to references to all QuickFixes which the QuickFix group contains. <example>
                            <p>The QuickFix group has the ID groupid and contains the QuickFixes with the IDs fix1 and fix2.</p>
                            <p>The first <el>sch:assert</el> element refers to the QuickFixes fix1 and fix2 per QuickFix ID. The second one refers to the same QuickFixes per ID of the QuickFix group.</p>
                            <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sch:assert test="[...]" sqf:fix="fix1 fix2">[...]&lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;sch:assert test="[...]" sqf:fix="groupid">[...]&lt;/sch:assert>
&lt;sqf:group id="groupid">
     &lt;sqf:fix id="fix1"> [...] &lt;/sqf:fix>
     &lt;sqf:fix id="fix2"> [...] &lt;/sqf:fix>
&lt;/sqf:group></eg>
                        </example></p>
                </div3>
                <div3>
                    <head>Scope of QuickFixes and QuickFix groups</head>
                    <?oxy_comment_start author="Nico Kutscherauer" timestamp="20150418T145559+0200" comment="what happens in abstract patterns, abstract rules..."?>
                    <p>A QuickFix or a QuickFix group can be defined global or local. Local QuickFixes or QuickFix groups are declared inside of the <termref def="sch-rule">Schematron rule</termref> and only the <termref def="sch-assertion">assertions</termref> of this rule are able to refer to the QuickFixes or QuickFix group. Global QuickFixes or QuickFix groups are declared inside of the <el>sqf:fixes</el> element and available for all <termref def="sch-assertion">Schematron assertions</termref>.</p>
                    <?oxy_comment_end?>
                    <example>
                        <p>Example for a global QuickFix:</p>
                        <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sch:schema> 
     [...] 
     &lt;sqf:fixes>
          &lt;sqf:fix id="fix2"> [...] &lt;/sqf:fix>
     &lt;/sqf:fixes>
&lt;/sch:schema></eg>
                    </example>
                    <example>
                        <p>Example for a local QuickFix:</p>
                        <eg xml:space="preserve">&lt;sch:rule context="[...]">
     [...] 
     &lt;sqf:fix id="fix1"> [...] &lt;/sqf:fix>
&lt;/sch:rule></eg>
                    </example>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="change-commands">
                <head>Change commands</head>
                <p>A QuickFix needs at least one change command. A change command is implemented by an activity element (see element group <titleref href="#sqf_activityElements"><phrase><code>sqf:activityElements</code></phrase></titleref>). A change command is processed relative to an <titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">anchor node</titleref>.</p>
                <div3 id="change-command-anchor-node">
                    <head>Anchor node</head>
                    <p>The anchor node is the context of a change command. By default the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref> is the anchor node.</p>
                    <p>To specify anchor nodes, the <att>match</att> attribute is provided to each activity element. If an activity element points to more than one anchor node, for each anchor node the change command will be executed. If an activity element points to no anchor node, no change command will be executed.</p>
                </div3>
                <div3>
                    <head>Conditions</head>
                    <p>Each change command can have a condition to execute. Therefore the attribute <att>use-when</att> is provided to each activity element. The condition will be defined in the <termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron errors</termref>. If the condition is not satisfied the change command should not be executed.</p>
                </div3>
                <div3>
                    <head>Create new content</head>
                    <p>Depending of the <titleref href="#change-command-kind">kind</titleref>, the change command may create new content to insert it into or replace nodes from the <termref def="sch-document">document to be fixed</termref>. There are three ways to create new content:</p>
                    <div4 id="create-by-sqf-att">
                        <head>By SQF attributes</head>
                        <p>To create a new node, the change command may provide the attributes <att>type</att> and <att>target</att>. This attributes create exact one node.</p>
                        <p>To create a new node the attribute type provides the following values:<ulist>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>keep</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create a node from the same type as the anchor node.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>element</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create a element.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>attribute</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create a attribute</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>processing-instruction</attval> or <attval>pi</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create a processing instruction</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p><attval>comment</attval></p>
                                    <p>To create a comment</p>
                                </item>
                            </ulist></p>
                        <p>If the <att>type</att> attribute has not the value <attval>comment</attval>, the attribute <att>target</att> is required. It sets the name of the created node. The value of the <att>target</att> attribute will be interpreted as an <titleref href="#attribute-value-template">attribute value template</titleref>. The effective value should be valid to the XSD type xs:QName.</p>
                        <p>If an Activity Element has an target attribute, the type attribute is required.</p>
                        <p>If the <att>type</att> attribute has the value <attval>element</attval> (or <attval>keep</attval> and the anchor element is an element), the content of the new element will be created <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the Activity Element</titleref>.</p>
                        <p>If the <att>type</att> attribute has the values <attval>attribute</attval>, <attval>processing-instruction</attval>, <attval>pi</attval> or <attval>comment</attval> (or <attval>keep</attval> and the anchor node is not an element), the value of the new node will be created <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the Activity Element</titleref>. If this returns nodes, the value will be created by the values of this nodes. More than one node value will be connected to one node value separated by whitespace.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="create-by-xpath">
                        <head>By an XPath expression</head>
                        <p>To define the new content by an XPath expression, the <att>select</att> attribute is provided. </p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>If the XPath expression returns an atomic value, the value will be transformed into an text node.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>If the XPath expression returns a sequence of atomic values, all values will be transformed to a text node. The values will be separated by whitespace.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p><?oxy_comment_start author="Nico Kutscherauer" timestamp="20150511T121134+0200" comment="Shall it be free to the implementation, whether it is a deep copy or like a &quot;apply-templates&quot; which respects other change commands?"?>If the XPath expression returns one or more nodes, the nodes will be copied into the <termref def="sch-document">document to be fixed</termref>.<?oxy_comment_end?></p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                        <p>If the Activity Element has a <att>select</att> attribute, the element should be empty.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4 id="create-by-content">
                        <head>By the Activity Element content</head>
                        <p>The content of the Activity Elements has the same functionality as the content of <el>xsl:template</el> elements from the <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20">XSLT 2.0 Recommendation</titleref>. This means:</p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Elements from the XSLT namespace will be processed in the context of the change command. If XSLT elements are able to change the context in XSLT, this should have the same effect to there descendents in SQF.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Elements which not belong to the XSLT, SQF or Schematron namespace will be processed as <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#dt-literal-result-element">Literal Result Elements</titleref>.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                        <p>Extensions of the XSLT template behavior:</p>
                        <ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Elements from the SQF namespace will be processed as it is defined in this specification. Permitted elements are:<ulist>
                                        <item>
                                            <p><el>sqf:keep</el></p>
                                        </item>
                                    </ulist></p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Elements from the Schematron namespace will be processed as it is defined in the Schematron specification. Permitted elements are:<ulist>
                                        <item>
                                            <p><el>sch:let</el></p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                            <p><el>sch:value-of</el></p>
                                        </item>
                                        <item>
                                            <p><el>sch:name</el></p>
                                        </item>
                                    </ulist></p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="conflicts">
                    <head>Conflicts</head>
                    <p>A conflict is thrown, if there are more than one change command for the same anchor node, during an QuickFix execution. There are two kinds of conflicts:<ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Resolvable conflict</p>
                                <p>If the conflict is between two or more change commands which belongs to the same QuickFix, the conflict is resolvable. In this case, the change command will be executed, whose activity element is defined at first inside of the <el>sqf:fix</el> element.</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Warning raised conflict</p>
                                <p>If two or more change commands from different QuickFixes are in conflict, the conflict is not resolvable. A warning should be produced. The implementation is free to decide which QuickFix has hire priority. This kind of a conflict is just possible, if an implementation allows to execute more than one QuickFix at once.</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist></p>
                </div3>
                <div3>
                    <head id="change-command-kind">Kind of the change commands</head>
                    <p>There are four predefined kinds of change commands:<ulist>
                            <item>
                                <p>Add</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Delete</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Replace</p>
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>StringReplace</p>
                            </item>
                        </ulist></p>
                    <glist>
                        <gitem>
                            <label>Delete</label>
                            <def>
                                <p>Deletes the anchor node.</p>
                            </def>
                        </gitem>
                        <gitem>
                            <label>Replace</label>
                            <def>
                                <p>Replaces the anchor node by one or more nodes.</p>
                            </def>
                        </gitem>
                        <gitem>
                            <label>StringReplace</label>
                            <def>
                                <p>Replaces substrings of the anchor node by one or more nodes. The anchor node needs to be a text node for this change command.</p>
                            </def>
                        </gitem>
                    </glist>
                    <p>A Schematron QuickFix implementation is free to provide extending Change commands. The extending change commands should provide the attributes of the attribute group <titleref href="#sqf_activityBase"><phrase><code>activityBase</code></phrase></titleref>.</p>
                    <div4>
                        <head>Add</head>
                        <p>Creates one or more nodes and insert it relative to the anchor node. The new content can be created by the <titleref href="#create-by-sqf-att">SQF attributes</titleref>, <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the sqf:replace element</titleref>.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4>
                        <head>Delete</head>
                        <p>This change command deletes the anchor node.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4>
                        <head>Replace</head>
                        <p>The anchor node will be replaced by new content. The new content can be created by the <titleref href="#create-by-sqf-att">SQF attributes</titleref>, <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the sqf:replace element</titleref>.</p>
                    </div4>
                    <div4>
                        <head>StringReplace</head>
                        <p>The anchor node has to be a text node. To analyze the text node, the <att>regex</att> attribute is required. The attribute value of the regex attribute will be interpreted as an <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#attribute-value-templates">attribute value template</titleref>. The effective value should be a valid <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#regular-expressions">Regular Expression</titleref> corresponding to the XSLT 2.0 Recommendation.</p>
                        <p>Any substrings, which matches to this Regular Expression, will be replaced by new content. The new content can be created <titleref href="#create-by-xpath">by XPath</titleref> or <titleref href="#create-by-content">by the content of the sqf:stringReplace element</titleref>.</p>
                    </div4>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>User Entry</head>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Variables and parameter</head>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Embedding XPath</head>
                <p>Schematron QuickFix is based on the W3C Recommendation XPath 2.0. Any XPath expression of the Schematron schema needs to match the syntax allowed by the XPath grammar.</p>
                <div3>
                    <head>Attributes to embed XPath expressions</head>
                    <p>The following table shows attributes, whose value will be parsed as XPath expressions, corresponding to the <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath20/">XPath 2.0</titleref> Recommendation:</p>
                    <p>
                        <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2">
                            <thead>
                                <tr>
                                    <th>Attribute</th>
                                    <th>Element</th>
                                    <th>Context</th>
                                    <th>Description</th>
                                    <th>Required return type</th>
                                </tr>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="2">default</td>
                                    <td>sqf:param</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Default value for the parameter</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:user-entry</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Default value for User Entry</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="4">match</td>
                                    <td>sqf:add</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Contexts of the change commands</td>
                                    <td>node()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:delete</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Contexts of the change commands</td>
                                    <td>node()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:replace</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Contexts of the change commands</td>
                                    <td>node()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:stringReplace</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Contexts of the change commands</td>
                                    <td>text()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="5">select</td>
                                    <td>sqf:add</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Nodes or atomic values, which should be inserted</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:keep</td>
                                    <td>Inherits from the parent node.</td>
                                    <td>Nodes to copy or apply to other change commands</td>
                                    <td>node()*</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:replace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Nodes or atomic values, which should be inserted</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:stringReplace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Nodes or atomic values, which should be inserted</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:with-param</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Value for the parameter</td>
                                    <td>no requirement</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="6">use-when</td>
                                    <td>sqf:add</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to process the change command</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:delete</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to process the change command</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:replace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to process the change command</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:stringReplace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to process the change command</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:fix</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to provide the QuickFix</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:group</td>
                                    <td><termref def="sch-error-context">context of the Schematron error</termref></td>
                                    <td>Condition to provide all QuickFixes of this QuickFix group</td>
                                    <td>no requirement, interpreted as boolean</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                </div3>
                <div3 id="attribute-value-template">
                    <head>Attribute Value Template</head>
                    <p>The following table shows attributes, whose value is interpreted as <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#attribute-value-templates">attribute value template</titleref> corresponding to the XSLT 2.0 Recommendation:</p>
                    <p>
                        <table border="1" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="2">
                            <thead>
                                <tr>
                                    <th>Attribute</th>
                                    <th>Element</th>
                                    <th>Context</th>
                                    <th>Effective value requirements</th>
                                </tr>
                            </thead>
                            <tbody>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>regex</td>
                                    <td>sqf:stringReplace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>Valid <titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#regular-expressions">Regular Expression</titleref> corresponding to the XSLT 2.0 Recommendation.</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td rowspan="2">target</td>
                                    <td>sqf:add</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>xs:QName</td>
                                </tr>
                                <tr>
                                    <td>sqf:replace</td>
                                    <td><titleref href="#change-command-anchor-node">Anchor node</titleref></td>
                                    <td>xs:QName</td>
                                </tr>
                            </tbody>
                        </table>
                    </p>
                    <p>The effective value requirements should be satisfied after interpreting the attribute value template.</p>
                </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>Localisation</head>
            </div2>
        </div1>
        <div1>
            <head>Implementation <?oxy_comment_start author="Nico Kutscherauer" timestamp="20150511T141452+0200" comment="move to appendix?"?>modes<?oxy_comment_end?></head>
            <p>A QuickFix can be implemented in two different modes:<ulist>
                    <item>
                        <p>XML save mode</p>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <p>XSLT only mode</p>
                    </item>
                </ulist></p>
            <p>An implementation is free to implement only one or both modes.</p>
            <div2>
                <head>XML save mode</head>
                <p>The XML save mode requires that no changes will be applied to the <termref def="sch-document">document to be fixed</termref>, which are not defined by the executed QuickFix. Changes which are caused by an XSLT processor (skip the XML declaration, resolving default attributes, CDATA sections, etc.) any time, should not influence the document. That is why it is not possible to implement the XML save mode with only XSLT processes.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2>
                <head>XSLT only mode</head>
                <p>If an implementation is based only on XSLT processes, this is called the XSLT only mode. In this case, it is allowed to change the <termref def="sch-document">document to be fixed</termref> on any QuickFix execution in the following ways, though it is not defined in the QuickFix:<ulist>
                        <item>
                            <p>Skip the XML declaration</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Skip the DOCTYPE declaration</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Skip whitespace:<ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>which are outside of the root element and not in processing instructions and comments.</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>non significant whitespace</p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist></p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Normalize whitespace<ulist>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>Leading whitespace of content in processing instructions in prolog</p>
                                    </item>
                                    <item>
                                        <p>between attributes</p>
                                    </item>
                                </ulist></p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Resolve default attributes to encoded attributes</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Resolve CDATA sections</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p>Resolve Character entities.</p>
                        </item>
                    </ulist></p>
            </div2>
        </div1>
        <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="SQFSpec_Elements.xml">
            <xi:fallback>
                <div1>
                    <head>No reference available</head>
                </div1>
            </xi:fallback>
        </xi:include>
    </body>
    <back>
        <div1>
            <head>Schematron Quick Fixes schema</head>
            <eg><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../schemas/schematron-quickFix.xsd" parse="text"/></eg>
        </div1>
    </back>
</spec>
